Mary Myart Malott Papers AAA 9034
Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, Texas Art Project Microfilm
Mary Myart Malott Papers
1954-1981
Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, Texas Art Project Microfilm
Malott, Mary Myart, 1928-2008
AAA 9034
3,681 Images
Biographical / Historical
Mary Myart Malott was born in Harell, Indiana in 1928 and died in Brooklyn, New York in 2008. Malott graduated from Radcliff College and received her MFA from The University of Texas. An artist, painter, sculptor, assemblage artist, art critic, and diarist, Mallot lived and worked primarily in Austin, TX, and New York. She wrote a weekly column from 1975 to 1978 for the Austin American-Statesman where she reviewed the work of artists such as Frida Kahlo and many others. An active artist and critic she also appeared weekly on KLRU Austin's "ArtBeat." In 1976, she won the Austin Chapter of the American Institute of Architects Award, and the Heritage Society of Austin's Historic Preservation Award for her work on preserving Austin's Pecan Square. In addition, she and her daughter, Sylvia McIntyre, rehabilitated the "Gilfillan House" in Austin, TX. Mallot's art has been exhibited throughout Texas and elsewhere in venues such as Laguna Gloria, the Huntington Gallery, the Elisabeth Ney Museum, The University of Texas, the Abilene Fine Arts Museum, Southwestern University, Baylor University, University of Houston, and the McNay Art Museum. Mallot relocated to New York in the 1980's and began exhibiting her work in New York City in the late 1980's and early 1990's. The 1994 exhibit of her complete "Slices of the Forest" series at the Amos Eno Gallery in SoHo was her last.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence; writings; photographs; legal and business records; a resume; journals; a notebook; exhibition catalogs and announcements; clippings; and printed material.
Other Finding Aids
Archives of American Art online guide at https://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/mary-myart-malott-papers-9034.
Conditions Governing Access
The Archives of American art does not own the original papers. Use is limited to the microfilm copy. Reel 2832: ACCESS RESTRICTED: written permission required. Microfilm reels 2833-2837 available for use at Archives of American Art offices; the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston Archives; and through interlibrary loan.
Acquisition Information
Lent for microfilming 1981 by Mary Myart Malott. Microfilmed as part of the Archives of American Art's Texas project.
Note: The Mary Myart Mallot Papers were microfilmed for the Texas Art Project at the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston as part of the Smithsonian Institution's Archives of American Art. Currently the papers can be accessed on microfilm at the MFAH. The University of Houston Libraries and the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston are digitizing these papers as part of a collaborative TexTreasures 2020 grant project through the Texas State Library and Archives Commission (TSLAC) with funding from the U.S. Institute of Museum and Library Services (IMLS).When digitization is complete, these papers will be made available online through UH Libraries and MFAH websites.
Women painters; Women sculptors; TexTreasures -- 2020; Schapiro, Miriam; Canaday, John Edwin
- Biographical Information (Reel 2833, Image 471-479)
- Correspondence, 1954-1981; undated
  - Correspondence, 1954-1964 (Reel 2833, Image 480-674)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Reel 2833, Image 675-834)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Reel 2834, Image 5-170)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Reel 2834, Image 171-287)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Reel 2834, Image 288-427)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Reel 2834, Image 428-557)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Reel 2834, Image 558-611)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Reel 2834, Image 612-765)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Reel 2834, Image 766-911)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Reel 2834, Image 912-1136)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Reel 2835, Image 5-80)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Reel 2835, Image 81-257)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Reel 2835, Image 258-342)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Reel 2835, Image 343-644)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Reel 2835, Image 645-931)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Reel 2835, Image 932-1129)
  - Correspondence (Cont'd), 1979 (Reel 2836, Image 5-173)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Reel 2836, Image 174-403)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Reel 2836, Image 404-463)
- Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1964; before (Reel 2836, Image 464-476)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1965 (Reel 2836, Image 477-491)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1966 (Reel 2836, Image 492-512)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1967 (Reel 2836, Image 513-534)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1968 (Reel 2836, Image 535-548)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1969 (Reel 2836, Image 549-572)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1970 (Reel 2836, Image 573-624)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1971 (Reel 2836, Image 625-641)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1972 (Reel 2836, Image 642-659)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1973 (Reel 2836, Image 660-666)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1974 (Reel 2836, Image 667-679)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1975 (Reel 2836, Image 680-698)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1976 (Reel 2836, Image 699-706)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1977 (Reel 2836, Image 707-732)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1978 (Reel 2836, Image 733-735)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1979 (Reel 2836, Image 736-767)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1980 (Reel 2836, Image 768-789)
  - Announcements, Clippings, Catalogues, 1981 (Reel 2836, Image 790-812)
- Thesis for Master of Fine Arts, University of Texas, 1970 (Reel 2836, Image 813-845)
- Guest Book, 1976-1981 (Reel 2836, Image 846-858)
- Articles Written by Malott
  - Articles written for Austin American-Statesman, May 1975-December 1976 (Reel 2836, Image 859-929)
  - Articles written for Austin American-Statesman, 1977 (Reel 2837, Image 5-55)
  - Articles written for Austin American-Statesman, 1978 (Reel 2837, Image 56-74)
  - Articles written for Austin American-Statesman, January-October 1978 (Reel 2837, Image 75-111)